Guide to the Washington Hood Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Washington Hood papers
1772-1861
WA MSS S-2687
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.46
(4 boxes) + 2 broadside folders
The papers consist of journals, correspondence, drawings, maps, architectural plans, family papers and business papers relating to Washington Hood, his father John McClellan Hood, and the Hood family. Journals document Hood's surveys of the Ohio and Michigan border in 1835 and of northeastern Oklahoma in 1839, and also include notes on painting and engineering. Family papers consist chiefly of correspondence and include letters to and from family members that describe Hood's expeditions. John Hood's business papers consist of correspondence, legal papers, and financial papers that document John Hood's personal finances and the business partnership of Hamilton and Hood in Philadelphia. One daguerreotype by photographer James M'Clees is included in the family papers, likely depicting John Hood circa 1850. Architectural plans include drawings that formed the basis of the Hood country home Bessie Bell in Limerick Township, Pennsylvania (built in 1834), and an 1834 proposal for a U.S. Government building designed to centralize executive staff. Maps include an early manuscript draft of Hood's 1835 map of Indian tribes west of Arkansas and Missouri. Printed maps depict charts and waterways in eastern North America.
Hood, Washington
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from William Reese Co. on the Frederick W. and Carrie S. Beinecke Fund for Western Americana and the Walter McClintock Memorial Fund, 2000.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Washington Hood, 1808-1840
Washington Hood (1808-1840), a cartographer and surveyor, was the son of John and Elizabeth Hood of Philadelphia. He graduated from the United States Military Academy in 1827 and served in the Corps of Engineers and the Corps of Topographical Engineers from 1829 until he became ill on an expedition in 1839. He died in 1840 at the age of 31. Among Hood's most frequently-cited surveys and maps are those of Indian territories west of the Mississipi, and of the border region between Ohio and Michigan.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of journals, correspondence, drawings, maps, architectural plans, family papers and business papers relating to Washington Hood, his father John McClellan Hood, and the Hood family. Journals document Hood's surveys of the Ohio and Michigan border in 1835 and of northeastern Oklahoma in 1839, and also include notes on painting and engineering. Family papers consist chiefly of correspondence and include letters to and from family members that describe Hood's expeditions. John Hood's business papers consist of correspondence, legal papers, and financial papers that document John Hood's personal finances and the business partnership of Hamilton and Hood in Philadelphia. One daguerreotype by photographer James M'Clees is included in the family papers, likely depicting John Hood circa 1850. Architectural plans include drawings that formed the basis of the Hood country home Bessie Bell in Limerick Township, Pennsylvania (built in 1834), and an 1834 proposal for a U.S. Government building designed to centralize executive staff. Maps include an early manuscript draft of Hood's 1835 map of Indian tribes west of Arkansas and Missouri. Printed maps depict charts and waterways in eastern North America.
Arrangement
Organized into five series: I. Journals, 1834-1840. II. Correspondence, 1828-1840. III. John Hood and Hood Family Papers, 1787-1861. IV. Maps, 1829-1835. Series V. Architectural and Engineering Plans, 1772-1836.
Businessmen -- Pennsylvania -- Philadelphia; Cartographers -- West (U.S.); Indians of North America -- Maps; Maps -- West (U.S.); Surveyors -- West (U.S.); Limerick (Pa.); Philadelphia (Pa.); Ohio -- Boundaries; Ohio -- Surveys; Oklahoma -- Surveys; Michigan -- Boundaries; Michigan -- Surveys; West (U.S.) -- Surveys; Architectural drawings (visual works); Daguerreotypes (photographs); Maps -- West (U.S.) -- 19th century; Businessmen -- Pennsylvania -- Philadelphia; Cartographers -- West (U.S.) -- 19th century; Surveyors -- West (U.S.) -- 19th century; Hood, Washington; Hood, John M., 1778-1848; M'Clees, Jas. E. (James E.); United States. War Department. Corps of Engineers; United States. Army. Corps of Topographical Engineers
- Journals, 1834-1840; Series I; 0.42; (1 box)
  Arrangement
  Arranged by subject matter.
  Scope and Contents
  Journals document Washington Hood's studies of engineering and painting, and his expeditions to Ohio, Michigan, Oklahoma, Missouri, and Arkansas.
  - Journals containing notes on painting and engineering, 1834-1840, undated (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Journals containing notes on the Ohio and Michigan borders, including commentary on Robert E. Lee, 1835-1840 (Box 1, Folder 3-5)
  - Journal containing "Field notes of the Eastern Boundaries of Indian lands", 1839 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Documents surveys in Oklahoma, Missouri, and Arkansas.
    Accompanied by a manuscript map of northeastern Oklahoma by General Matthew Arbuckle.
- Correspondence, 1828-1840; Series II; 0.21; (1 box)
  Organized into folders by type of correspondent.
  Washington Hood correspondence consists of incoming letters from friends (chiefly fellow military officers) and family members, and copies of third-party letters relating to Hood's service in the Corps of Engineers. Correspondents include Robert Anderson, Thomas Barker, and John Bell.
  - Correspondence from friends, 1828-1840 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence from family members, 1824-1837 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence relating to Hood's service in the Corps of Engineers, 1830-1839 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- John Hood and Hood Family Papers, 1787-1861; Series III; 0.84; (2 boxes)
  Not arranged in any particular order.
  Series III consists of business and family papers. John Hood business papers include financial records and correspondence related to the management of John Hood's merchant business Hamilton and Hood. Legal documents consist of deeds and contracts. Family correspondence consists of letters among Hood family members.
  - Hood family copy of Jenkins's Vest-Pocket Lexicon, 1861 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Hood family correspondence, 1828-1843 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - John Hood correspondence, 1815-1836 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - John Hood business papers, 1795-1856 (Box 3, Folder 13-16)
  - Legal documents, 1787-1843 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Seal stamp, undated (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Woodblock image of John Hood by V. Grottenthaler, Philadelphia, circa 1850 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Daguerreotype of John Hood by James M'Clees, Philadelphia, circa 1850 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Unsorted family papers, 1821-1839, undated (Box 4, Folder 21)
- Maps, 1829-1835; Series IV; (1 portfolio)
  Organized by geographical area.
  Series IV consists of a manuscript map of Nebraska and Iowa focusing on the territory of local Indian tribes, and of charts and maps of waterways depicting New York State, Ontario, Rhode Island, Florida, and Louisiana. While some maps are undated, all material dates from the mid-nineteenth century.
  - Manuscript map of Nebraska and Iowa, before 1835 (Box 5 Broadside)
  - Survey for a canal in the vicinity of Niagara Falls, New York, undated (Box 5 Broadside)
  - Profiles of the Niagara River at Lewiston, New York, 1835 (Box 5 Broadside)
  - Map of the Breach at the head of Presqu'ile Bay, 1835 (Box 5 Broadside)
  - Chart of Newport and Conanicut Island, Rhode Island, undated (Box 5 Broadside)
  - Chart of Tampa Bay, Florida, undated (Box 5 Broadside)
  - Chart of St George Island, Florida, 1829 (Box 5 Broadside)
  - Chart of the mouth of the Mississippi River, undated (Box 5 Broadside)
- Architectural and Engineering Plans, 1772-1836; Series V; (1 portfolio)
  Arranged chronologically.
  Series V consists of unattributed hydraulic engineering plans, and of architectural plans drawn by Washington Hood.
  - Hydraulic engineering plans, 1772 (Box 6 Broadside)
  - Plan for U.S. Executive offices, 1834; (3 drawings) (Box 6 Broadside)
  - Plan for Bessie Belle, 1834 (Box 6 Broadside)
  - Papers concerning the plan for U.S. Executive offices, 1834 (Box 6 Broadside)
  - Lighthouse proposed for the Brandywine Shoal, 1836 (Box 6 Broadside)